A Guide to the Papers of John Armstrong Chaloner, 1881-1933
Special Collections, University of Virginia Library
Special Collections, University of Virginia Library
Papers of John Armstrong Chaloner 1881-1933
Special Collections, University of Virginia Library
38-394-a, -b
Ca. 2,000 items (5 boxes, 2 linear feet).
Administrative Information
Access Restrictions
There are no restrictions.
Acquisition Information
The papers were a gift to the Library of the John Armstrong Chaloner Estate ca. 1935.
Biographical/Historical Information
A brief biography of Chaloner and his Albemarle County estate "Merry Mill" may be found in Volume 73, January 1965, of The Virginia Magazine of History and Biography, pp. 3-21. The article's chronological history of Chaloner's many lawsuits and explanation of his "X-Faculty" which enabled him to write will no doubt be of help to any researcher.
The correspondence, mostly copies of letters written by Chaloner, gives a colorful picture of his character and personality. Correspondence received from others is often covered with comments written in blue pencil or crayon. Unfortunately Chaloner's handwriting is difficult to read and his notes sometimes obscure the original letter.
The legal papers are largely copies of briefs field with the court and testimony taken from court records. These are both in typescript and printed. Since Chaloner was a member of the New York Bar, he often wrote out drafts of briefs for his lawyers in blue colored pencil. Chaloner eventually changed his last name to "Chanler," which accounts for both spellings appearing attached to various documents.
Chaloner's literary writing was all done through his "X-Faculty" which took over his mind. All of his manuscripts are written in blue colored pencil and annotated in red. Many of his poems or plays which were published are in typescript. There are also galley proofs of his magazine "Scorpio" and his play Brief for Defense.
Scope and Content
The John Armstrong Chaloner Papers, 1881-1933, consist of ca. 2000 items (2 linear feet) largely correspondence, legal papers and briefs concerning his many law suits (some on charitable and business matters) and copies of his poetry and plays. There are fragments of briefs from his law suits and Chaloner's notes on them. Prominent among them are Washington Post vs. Chaloner, 1917; and Chaloner vs. Sherman and related property restitution trials, 1908-16.
There are also manuscript or galleys for "Robbery under law," "A brief for the defense...," "The serpent of the Old Nile," "The infernal comedy--Hell per a spirit message therefrom," "An answer to Omar Khayyam," and "Scorpio," copies of "The Confederacy and the solid south,"and "The X-faculty," as well as reviews and notes for "Lunacy Law of the World." There are also papers re the J. A. Chaloner Paris prize foundation, the McCormick-Chaloner eclipse expedition, 1927, his program to bring movies to rural America, and the "Lost city of Nevada" pageant he sponsored.
The collection also contains a 1913 letter to William H. Taft requesting safe conduct to Washington D.C. to impeach district court of New York Judge George Chandler Holt and clippings re Chaloner and the Merry Mills and a photograph of a document signed by Napoleon that was owned by Chaloner. Other correspondents include Lewis Stuyvesant Chanler, John W. Fishburne, Armistead Churchill Gordon, John Henry Ingram, George Perkins, and Anselm Phelps.
Arrangement
The papers are divided into two segments: the first consists of correspondence, bills, and receipts arranged chronologically. The second includes all other papers arranged chronologically where possible, and alphabetically if undated.
Contents List
- Correspondence 1881-1930, 3 folders (Box 1)
- 3 Tablets containing notes and copies of letters & wires 1919 (Box 1)
- Telegrams 1892-1925 (Box 1)
- Bills, Receipts, & Accounts 1892-1930 (Box 1)
- Undated Correspondence and Miscellaneous envelopes with notes n.d. (Box 1)
- J.A. Chaloner Paris Prize Foundation 1890-1921 (Box 2)
- Fragment of printed testimony re Chaloner's sanity 1900 (Box 2)
- Proof that notice of Albemarle County Court proceeding was given the other side 1901 (Box 2)
- Notes on brief probably for Supreme Court 1903 (Box 2)
- Notes & Review of Chaloner's Book on Lunacy Laws; notes on the Automobile Law in Virginia 1903 (Box 2)
- Chaloner vs. Sherman, Bill of Exceptions and Exhibits U.S. District Court 1904 (Box 2)
- Index to two unidentified briefs 1905 (Box 2)
- New York Herald story on J.A. Chaloner 1906 (Box 2)
- Petition of J.A. Chaloner to U.S. Supreme Court 1906 (Box 2)
- Lunacy Law of the World by J.A. Chaloner 1907 (Box 2)
- "Scorpio" by J.A. Chaloner, pages removed from bound edition 1907 (Box 2)
- "Answer to Deposition" by Chaloner 1907 February 20, AMs (Box 2)
- J.A. Chaloner ads. William Dike Reed Memorandum of Argument 1907 (Box 2)
- Appeal by Chanler to Circuit Court of Appeals in Chanler vs. Sherman 1908 May 11 (Box 2)
- Briefs for John Chanler vs. Thomas Sherman before the Supreme Court 1908-1916 (Box 2)
- The Academy, a Weekly Review 1908 (Box 2)
- Automobile Law 1909 (Box 2)
- Virginia Law Register - Articles on Law re Insanity & Incompetence 1910 May-June (Box 2)
- Chaloner vs. New York Evening Post - Brief on behalf of Plaintiff in Opposition to Demurrer 1910 October 1915 (Box 2)
- Miscellaneous items 1910 (Box 2)
- Menu & Songbook of Delta Psi Dinner in Richmond 1910 December 29 (Box 2)
- Programme of Grand Opening of Chaloner Theater in New York 1922 December 21 (Box 2)
- Menu for John B. McDonald Dinner at Manhattan Club 1904 December (Box 2)
- "The X-Faculty" or "The Pythagorean Triangle of Psychology" 1911 (Box 2)
- Petition for the Impeachment of Judge George C. Holt 1912 May 13 (Box 2)
- Articles re McCormick-Chaloner Party Ready for Observations 1912 (Box 2)
- Petition for impeachment of G.C. Holt 1912 (Box 2)
- Letter to President Taft with enclosures 1913 February 6 (Box 3)
- Lists of those Newspapers & Universities receiving copies of "Scorpio" & other works 1913 (Box 3)
- Appeal of John A. Chaloner to the State of South Carolina 1913 (Box 3)
- "Robbery Under Law," a play, by J.A. Chaloner 1914, AMs (Box 3)
- Religious, Divine Related Items 1914-1923 (Box 3)
- Reviews of and Printed Copy of "Robbery Under Law" 1915 (Box 3)
- Brief in Rebuttal 1916 July 27 (Box 3)
- Washington Post Company vs. Chaloner 1917 (Box 3)
- Chaloner vs. Dunn 1921 (Box 3)
- Testimony in case of John A. Chaloner vs. Washington Post Company in Supreme Court District of Columbia 1922 January 26 (Box 3)
- Charge to the Jury in John A. Chaloner vs. Washington Post Company in Supreme Court District of Columbia 1922 January 30 (Box 3)
- Movies for the Farmers, v. 1 & 2 1922 (Box 3)
- Briefs in Libel Trial of Chaloner vs. Washington Post Company ca. 1922 (Box 3)
- Communication with Miss Jessup through Chaloner's X-Faculty 1923 March 9 (Box 3)
- Fragment of article dedicated to Bishop Manning ( Brief for Defense ) 1923 August 27 (Box 3)
- Instructions to Publisher & Footnotes for Unidentified article by Chaloner 1923-1924 (Box 3)
- Letter to County Judge Taylor re Lunacy Laws 1924 March 22, 2 copies (Box 3)
- Galley proofs for "Little Brief For Defense" ca. 1924 (Box 3)
- Brief for defence ca. 1924 (Box 3)
- Proofs & Reviews for Brief for Defense ca. 1924 (Box 4)
- Aeronautical Bulletin Information on Landing Field on Chaloner Estate 1925 (Box 4)
- The Lost City of Nevada Pageant 1925-1926 (Box 4)
- Expeditions to Norway to see Eclipse financed by Chaloner 1927 (Box 4)
- Relations between Cuba and the U.S. Institute of Public Affairs, University of Virginia 1933 (Box 4)
- Copies of articles from Newspapers & Magazines n.d. (Box 4)
- 2 copies of article n.d., TMs (Box 4)
- Clippings about Chaloner, Amelie Rives & Prince Troubetzkoy n.d. (Box 4)
- Copy of Article from Literary Digest on Coolidge Speech n.d. (Box 4)
- Dates found in "Four Years Behind the Bars of 'Bloomingdale' " n.d., TMs (Box 4)
- Extracts from brief argued before the Supreme Court n.d. (Box 4)
- Extracts from Judge Sidney J. Dudley's Brief in Reed vs. Chaloner n.d. (Box 4)
- Fragments of various court & legal proceedings n.d. (Box 4)
- Galleys for "Scorpio" n.d. (Box 4)
- Legal briefs re the numerous suits to which Chaloner was a party n.d. (Box 4)
- "Merry Mill" Estate and J.A. Chaloner n.d. (Box 4)
  Pictures and descriptions
- Miscellaneous parts of brief & articles by Chaloner n.d. (Box 4)
- Miscellaneous & Fragments n.d. (Box 5)
- "No Times for the Satirist" & Review of "Scorpio" 1915-1918 (Box 5)
- Notes on brief n.d. (Box 5)
- A novel, Thorns & Orange Blossoms, by Bertha M. Clay n.d. (Box 5)
  Chaloner notes & underlining
- Photographs & 1908 Calendar with notes written on back, J. Armstrong Chanler calling card n.d. (Box 5)
- Poem - "The Infernal Comedy," "In Memoriam Durante" n.d. (Box 5)
- Poem - "Serpent of the Old Nile" n.d. (Box 5)
- "The Rubaiyat of Omar Khayyam" & "An Answer to Omar Khayyam" n.d. (Box 5)
- Sonnets probably written for "Scorpio" n.d. (Box 5)
- Third Lecture given by Chaloner at the Cort Theatre on the X-Faculty and the Subconscious n.d. (Box 5)
- Transcript of Testimony in suit against the New York Evening Post n.d. (Box 5)
- Transcript of Testimony in unidentified court proceedings re J.A. Chaloner n.d. (Box 5)
- Untitled poems, probably written for "Scorpio" n.d. (Box 5)
- Various printed pamphlets & fragments n.d. (Box 5)
- Photograph of Armée d'Italie, no 137 au citoyen Chauvet 1920 January 30 (Box 5)
  Commissaire [Mar 29, 1796] signed Bonapart. Annotated as being in the possession of Chaloner.